BUNDI THOMAS

Phone Number: +254(0)727639800

Email: bundithomas@outlook.com; tbundi@strathmore.edu Skype: bundithomas

Profile

Thomas has a keen interest in sustainable renewable energy generation and energy efficiency through capacity building, research, standards development, quality assurance and system design best practice. His research interests are on solar photovoltaics, solar thermal, information technology, design thinking, and renewable energy solutions for rural electrification and productive use. My current responsibilities as the quality engineer is to participate in development of electrotechnical standards, lead in testing of solar PV systems and components following various standards, train in professional courses and lead or technical support in projects at the Centre.

Educational background

BSc Mechatronic Engineering, Dedan Kimathi University of Technology, 2012 – 2016

Kenya School of Secondary Education, Lenana School, 2008 – 2011

Professional qualifications/ memberships

	ings undertaken
Feb 2018	Licensed T3 SPV technician with EPRA (ERC/SPVT/00604).
Jun 2018	Member Association of Energy Professionals Eastern Africa (AEPEA)
Nov 2017	Registered graduate engineer with EBK.

Sep 2019	Personal Leadership Programme, SU
Jun 2019	Challenge Driven Education and Design Thinking, SU and KTH
Mar 2019	Solar cooling workshop on promoting agricultural value chains, SERC
Nov 2018	Pilot training of trainers on Solar powered irrigation systems toolbox, GIZ, energypedia.
Mar 2018	Solar water pumping Training of Trainers, SERC
Feb 2018	Solar thermal (water heating) training, SERC
Feb 2018	ISO 17025:2017 Implementers' course training - SERC
Jan 2018	Micro-Grid Academy training - KPLC, SERC, Res4Africa, AVSI
Nov 2017	National Industrial Training Authority & RENAC Solar training curriculum review.
Sep 2017	Solar photovoltaics technician training on grid connected and hybrid systems, SERC
Apr 2017	Solar photovoltaics technician training on stand-alone systems, SERC

Work experience

Jun 2018- Present	Quality .	Engine	ngineer,	
	C1		т	

Strathmore Energy Research Centre.

Mar 2017- Jun 2018 Engineering Trainee,

Strathmore Energy Research Centre.

Jan 2017-Mar 2017 *Intern,*

Strathmore Energy Research Centre.

Jan 2016- Mar 2016 Attaché,

Central glass industries Ltd. Forming Department.

Key Projects illustrating work experience

Name of project	Oxfam Project: Training on Solar Water Pumping Systems		
Year	November, 2019		
Client	Oxfam GB.		
Main project	Capacity building to WASH engineers from selected development agencies in		
features	Somaliland on solar powered water pumping solutions. The training covered sizing selection of components, installation, operation and maintenance.		
Role	Lead trainer and course coordinator		
Achievements	 The participants were training on solar as a resource, its features and advantages. The participants were also training on best practices and rule of thumbs in borehole drilling and development, water quality, water pumps, pump controllers, solar PV water pipes and accessories. Finally, the participants were trained on the complete design of solar water pumping systems. 		
Name of project	Solar PV feasibility study and implementation supervision.		
Year	2019, ongoing.		
Client	AIC Kijabe Hospital.		
Main project	Consultancy project for conducting feasibility studies for a solar PV grid connected		
features	system, designing the solar system, bid management and supervision of the contractor during the installation phase.		
Role	Technical lead		
Achievements	1. Feasibility assessment on PV installation space, energy consumption analysis and design simulations.		
	2. Preparation of bill of materials with the required specifications.		
	3. Preparation of bid documents, analysis of bids submitted and the report ranking bids.		
	4. Supervision of the installation of the solar PV system.		
Name of project	Assessing opportunities for off grid cooling & processing in value chain promotion		
Year	2019		
Client	Deutsche Gesellschaft für Internationale Zusammenarbeit (GIZ) GmbH		
Main project	Conducting studies on the existing value chains in fish, vegetables and fruits in Kismayo		
features	and recommending low cost off-grid technologies in cooling and processing to		
icaiaico	promote livelihoods and quality of life.		
Role	Technical lead		
Achievements	 Design and propose recommendations on solar cooling and off-grid food processing technologies. 		
	 Recommendation on solar powered water treatment and desalination solutions. 		

Kismayo.

agencies.

3. High level summary on the existing value chains in fish, milk and vegetables in

Interview of key informants, stakeholders, ministry officials and development

Name of project	Specialized training on Hybrid Solar PV system operation and maintenance		
Year	2019		
Client	International Centre of Insect Physiology and Ecology (ICIPE, Kenya)		
Main project	Training solar PV system owner's engineering team on the optimum operation and		
features	maintenance of the plants at Nairobi and Mbita.		
Role	Project lead		
Achievements	1. Trained five electrical engineers on design and installation of grid connected and		
	hybrid solar PV systems		
	2. Conducted a site walk-through and interpreted the plant operation and layout.		
	3. Gave operation and maintenance recommendations based on the system setup.		
	4. Analysis and explanation of the system monitoring platform data.		
Name of project	Solar PV system audit on WeHUBs		
Year	2018		
Client	Siemens Stiftung		
Main project	Assessment and technical audit on eight stand-alone systems used for solar lantern		
features	charging, water purification and cybercafé in the western coast of Kenya to investigate		
	system integrity and advise on the performance status.		
Role	Technical lead		
Achievements	1. Verifying the AC and DC wiring connection integrity by measuring the insulation		
	resistance, continuity and earth resistance.		
	2. Checking the system configuration settings and correcting where necessary.		
	3. Recommending on the load expansion given the current system status.		
Name of project	Construction and Installation of a commercial rooftop, Grid Tie Solar PV plant		
Year	2018		
Client	Equatorial Energies		
Main project	Proposals for project management, design verification and interpretation of technical		
features	drawings for the construction and installation of a 850kWp solar PV system in Nakuru,		
Role	Kenya,		
Achievements	Design and technical associate 1. Verification of the shop drawings from the contractor on the installation of the DV.		
Acmevements	1. Verification of the shop drawings from the contractor on the installation of the PV module.		
	2. Preparation of a detailed workplan to ensure timely completion of the project.		
	3. Drafted the methods specifications matrix.		
Name of project	Feasibility and design of a Grid Tie Solar PV system		
Year	2018, ongoing.		
Client	Karen Country Club		
Main project	Consultancy services to determine the feasibility of a grid connected solar PV system,		
features	running design simulations, advise on project financing and preparation of bid		
	documents for the implementation of the project.		
Role	Project lead		
Achievements	1. Lead in the feasibility studies that analyzed the space requirements, the energy consumption trends, and other project constrains.		
	2. Presented the optimum solar PV system size that met one-third savings on the		
	electricity bills.		
	3. Presented the financing options available for the project implementation and		
	guided on the ideal model.		
	4. Prepared bid documents that will be advertised to get a contractor to install the		
	system.		
	•		

Name of project	Training of Trainers on solar PV stand-alone system		
Year	2018		
Client	International Labor Organization (ILO)		
Main project	The project involved training of twenty graduates, electrical technicians and engineers		
features	on the design, installation, operation and maintenance of off-grid, residential power		
	systems.		
Role	Lead trainer		
Achievements	1. The participants were trained based on the T1/T2 solar technicians training curriculum used in Kenya. They were trained on how to train others on the same course.		
	2. Guided in the assembly and use of solar mobile training kits developed by SERC in understanding stand-alone power systems.		
	3. Trained on best practice guidelines and use of tools and measuring equipment in installation.		
Name of project	Development of a Dual Axis Solar Tracking mechanism on a solar system		
Year	2016		
Main project	Development of a dual axis solar tracking mechanism on a solar system for maximum		
features	energy harvest. Project was submitted as a final year undergraduate group project.		
Role			
	Lead mechanical and electrical designer.		
Achievements	1. Lead in the CAD design and simulation of the mechanical structure up to fabrication.		
	2. Tested the prototype and confirmed that the light sensor diodes actuated the		

Name of project	ROBOKEN competition for academic institutions	
Year	2014	
Main project	Development of an autonomous guided vehicle (AVG) that would complete the game	
features	in the shortest time possible given a set of competition rules.	
Role	Mechanical draughtsman and design assistant.	
Achievements	1. First place finish in the 2014 competition, second runners up in 2015.	
	2. Prepared CAD drawings on the robot's chassis and servo arm.	
	3. Assistant in microchip programming and PCB fabrication.	

servomotors supporting the solar PV module to track the sun.

Hobbies

Reading on the history of and emerging technology, robotics, automation, automotive industry and energy related issues. Travelling, tinkering, data analysis and playing football.

Skills

Design and optimization of solar PV systems, capacity building and training in implementation of solar PV systems, research on renewable technologies, proficient in MS Office suite, moderate skills in mechanical and electrical CAD software. Fluent in speaking and writing English and Swahili.

Referees.

Eng. Christopher Gichere	Martin Kamande	Anne Wacera
Maintenance Engineer,	Lecturer,	Quality Manager,
Central Glass Industries Ltd.	Dedan Kimathi University of Tech.	Strathmore University.
E:cgichere@centralglass.co.ke	E:mikmartinirungu@gmail.com	E:awambugu@strathmore.edu
T: +254(20)5131272	T: +254 707 472 648	T: +254 703 344 396